<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-07-17T18:54:28-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">The Digital Self</title><subtitle>Are we looking after, and properly attending to our digital selves?</subtitle><author><name>Ki Lane</name></author><entry><title type="html">My Rocky Relationship With Facebook</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/healing/my-rocky-relationship-with-facebook/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Rocky Relationship With Facebook" /><published>2019-07-17T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-07-17T12:25:52-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/healing/my-rocky-relationship-with-facebook</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/healing/my-rocky-relationship-with-facebook/">&lt;p&gt;I thought this post would end up being lengthy and difficult to write, but honestly I’ve been working on my relationships with Facebook for some time now. I had cleaned up my profile a while back. Deleting all of my posts, comments, and other activity prior to 2017. Since then I haven’t used the site much. Before that I used it a lot. I can’t 100% ditch Facebook because there are some people on there I care about and will most likely never see again, or know how to get a hold of them without Facebook. However, I’ve reached a point with the platform that I will only look in there once or twice a day at the most, sometimes going days without looking in there at all, and I never ever use on my mobile devices—-I only use the web browser to peak in from time to time, and post infrequently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook doesn’t have any business value for me. My professional Facebook pages have never done very well. But it does still bring me some personal value from time to time. I began hitting a rocky point with Facebook in 2013 when I worked in Washington D.C. for the Obama administration as a Presidential Innovation Fellow. I would have staffers from the White House posting relevant policy matters in one post, and people I grew up with posting lynching photos in another—-forcing me to cull many people I grew up with. As we approached the 2016 election, another culling of individuals became reality after some pretty disturbing comments and posts from family and friends supporting Trump made their way across my timeline. Not to mention the endless trip of misinformation on vaccinations, brown people, Russians, and other topics that made the through my timeline on a regular basis. I just do not need this in my life. I do not need to be connected with these people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have my Facebook privacy settings narrowed down. I delete the application from my phone. I spend minimal time there, mostly fence-sitting, and rarely posting anything. I only use it to lightly stay up on what friends and family are doing, and as a lifeline to connect with folks I may not have any other way to connect with. I am better off without Facebook. I’m not nearly as depressed about things without these connections with Facebook’s algorithm in my face throughout the day. Facebook can be pretty toxic if you do not manage the people and topics you are exposed to. You do not have to maintain connections with people just because you knew them in high school. You don’t have to be friends with family members that make you uncomfortable, harass you, or let their friends harass you. You can stay in tune with the world, and maintain connections without Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It takes a while to ween yourself off the application, and the platform. Eventually you find the site pretty boring, and you begin to stop remember it exists if you can’t easily reach for it on your mobile phone. Facebook does get pretty desperate to get your attention and will be emailing you a lot, kind of like a jilted lover. However, over time things settle, and Facebook stops dominating your life, and driving your reality. You have to reduce the number of connections on the platform to a meaningful amount. You have to remove it from your mobile phone, and even go so far as to remove bookmarks and other convenient links to it. Make yourself work to get at it. Eventually it will fall into the background of your digital life. Ideally you are finding other things to do offline, and not just replacing Facebook with another digital distraction. Eventually you stop feeling the need to perform on the social platform, and your life gets back to some kind of normality—-hopefully an offline normality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook is the poster child for me of what technology should not be in our life. They have made it clear that they do not respect the privacy, security, and well-being of the users of their platform. They have made it clear that they choose advertising profits over the users of their platform. We are nothing but a raw material commodity to them, and they have demonstrated that they only do the bare minimum to keep our information safe, and us using their platform. How many times have they said they are sorry now? In return, they have now lost my trust. I won’t use their applications regularly. I will only put what data I need into their platform to stay up to date with a handful of friends. I have a rocky relationships with Facebook, and like many of the folks I’ve culled from Facebook, I don’t think we will be patching things up anytime soon. We just don’t see eye to eye when it comes to valuing humans over profit, politics, and stock market performance. I’m just too human centered to reconcile on this one.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ki Lane</name></author><category term="Social" /><summary type="html">I thought this post would end up being lengthy and difficult to write, but honestly I’ve been working on my relationships with Facebook for some time now. I had cleaned up my profile a while back. Deleting all of my posts, comments, and other activity prior to 2017. Since then I haven’t used the site much. Before that I used it a lot. I can’t 100% ditch Facebook because there are some people on there I care about and will most likely never see again, or know how to get a hold of them without Facebook. However, I’ve reached a point with the platform that I will only look in there once or twice a day at the most, sometimes going days without looking in there at all, and I never ever use on my mobile devices—-I only use the web browser to peak in from time to time, and post infrequently.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Using DuckDuckGo As My Search Engine</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/healing/using-duck-duck-go-as-my-search-engine/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Using DuckDuckGo As My Search Engine" /><published>2019-07-16T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-07-16T12:25:52-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/healing/using-duck-duck-go-as-my-search-engine</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/healing/using-duck-duck-go-as-my-search-engine/">&lt;p&gt;Continuing my evaluation of the technology I let into my life, I’ve switched from Google to DuckDuckGo as my primary search engine. After switching browsers, and ditching Google Chrome for Firefox, I wanted to also put over a decade of Google usage for web search behind me. I know my individual protest on the use of Google as a search engine will not make much of a dent in their bottom line, but it still matters to me. The less data exhaust I give to Google, the better. The less my life is used to train Google algorithms the better. I’ve been off Google Search for almost two weeks now, and I much prefer DuckDuckGo as my source of information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, so why DuckDuckGo? It says it right on the home page, “The search engine that doesn’t track you.” — that is all I ask. Provide me with a useful tool, carve out a sensible business model for you to generate revenue and keep the lights on, and we can do business. Honestly, it isn’t that much to ask. We should be able to do technology, provide server, desktop, and mobile applications that bring value, but do not surveil or exploit people. All I want is an application to be honest about what they are doing, and not keep secrets about how they make money, and what data they gather about me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spend a lot of time in the browser, and a lot of time searching the web. I just want access to a decent search engine to help find what I am looking for. I do not need every aspect of my life tracked and sold to the highest bidder, or even used to train predictive machine learning models. I don’t want to be worrying about what my search engine provider is up to. I don’t need companies having as much visibility as Google does into my life. Recently, I am all about minimizing the visibility Facebook, Google, and some other providers have into my life. I’m not advocating for boycotts of these platforms, as they still provide some value to me. I am just looking to minimize their reach in my life. Being more critical of which tools I use, why I use them, and spend more time scrutinizing and paying attention to the ethics of the company behind each tool I put to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not feel like I am missing out on any information. I feel like DuckDuckGo’s search results satisfy my personal and professional search needs. I still rely on Bing Search for my automated business search needs, as they are the only search engine with a real API for their search engine, which I can actually pay money to access. I am a little less concerned about companies like Microsoft having visibility into my professional world, than I am of companies like Google having visibility into my personal world. In the end, I’m pretty proud of myself for making this move. It feels like another significant shift in my digital landscape, one that really helps me better protect my digital self. Ensuring that I’m minimizing the surface area of my life that I willing to share with the technology companies I let into my life.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ki Lane</name></author><category term="Search" /><summary type="html">Continuing my evaluation of the technology I let into my life, I’ve switched from Google to DuckDuckGo as my primary search engine. After switching browsers, and ditching Google Chrome for Firefox, I wanted to also put over a decade of Google usage for web search behind me. I know my individual protest on the use of Google as a search engine will not make much of a dent in their bottom line, but it still matters to me. The less data exhaust I give to Google, the better. The less my life is used to train Google algorithms the better. I’ve been off Google Search for almost two weeks now, and I much prefer DuckDuckGo as my source of information.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Demoting Gmail In My Life</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/healing/demoting-gmail-in-my-life/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Demoting Gmail In My Life" /><published>2019-07-15T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-07-15T12:25:52-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/healing/demoting-gmail-in-my-life</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/healing/demoting-gmail-in-my-life/">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been on Gmail since the early days. It’s been my primary email account for about 15 years. Today, I am demoting it. I recently ditched Google Chrome as my browser, and now I want to reduce my footprint when it comes to their email services. I have three primary emails, kinlane@gmail.com, info@apievangelist.com, and info@kinlane.com (go ahead and spam me, doesn’t bother me—I won’t read it). I ran the kinlane.com domain on Google Apps, but apievangelist.com I ran on some company in Sweden. I am consolidating both of them with my domain registrar Hover, and using kinlane.com as my primary domain. I”ll be doing business on apievangelist.com, but will be only receiving email on kinlane@gmail.com. After a while, I’ll just stop using Gmail altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2019, I just do not want my personal and business world flowing through Google servers. I know they still have other ways of getting at my data, but I can work to minimize my footprint within the Google datacenter, and consolidate my email with a company I trust. I really have enjoyed Google Gmail services over the years. I was happy when they offered the Google Apps for Business, as I am happy to pay for my services. But, I’d say the damage has already been done by their approach to capturing data through their free services. My trust levels regarding Google services have be dimmed, and I will be evaluating each service I use for the usefulness of it in my world, and the overall benefits it delivers. My goal is to significantly reduce the size of my Google account, and the associated services. It isn’t easy trimming down an account like this, you have to make some hard decisions, but ultimately you’d be surprised how fast you adapt, and how minimal the overall impact on your life it all ends up being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not think I can completely remove Google from my life—-it just isn’t possible. They are that ubiquitous. However, I can work to minimize my usage of their products and services.  I’ve become quite dependent on some of what Google offers. Sometimes it is because it is a superior product, like Google Maps. Other times it is just through habit and convenience, like with Gmail. I like the Gmail application, and the overall service, but all of its features combined doesn’t outweigh the damage they are inflicting right now with their views of privacy and respect for the digital self. I can get comparable email services through the domain registrar I use (Hover), and not have to worry about them scanning my emails, or using the exhaust from my daily emailing to train their latest machine learning magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember when having a Gmail account was cool-—man, what a fool I was. I took the bait, hook, line and sinker. I have used kinlane@gmail.com for the last 14 years, and it feels strange to put it down. Honestly, it feels good. I don’t like I am giving so much control over my digital self to a company. I prefer only using email addresses within domains I can control. I can’t migrate my kinlane@gmail.com account—-it isn’t mine. This is a problem. I’m not sure why I ever thought it was a good idea to use a network email account in the first place. I’m even more confused why I continued to use it as my primary account for almost 15 years. Anyways, I’ll still be checking in on kinlane@gmail.com, but eventually I will stop tuning in, and if you haven’t emailed me at info@kinlane.com or kin@apievangelist.com, you probably won’t get a response.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ki Lane</name></author><category term="Email" /><summary type="html">I’ve been on Gmail since the early days. It’s been my primary email account for about 15 years. Today, I am demoting it. I recently ditched Google Chrome as my browser, and now I want to reduce my footprint when it comes to their email services. I have three primary emails, kinlane@gmail.com, info@apievangelist.com, and info@kinlane.com (go ahead and spam me, doesn’t bother me—I won’t read it). I ran the kinlane.com domain on Google Apps, but apievangelist.com I ran on some company in Sweden. I am consolidating both of them with my domain registrar Hover, and using kinlane.com as my primary domain. I”ll be doing business on apievangelist.com, but will be only receiving email on kinlane@gmail.com. After a while, I’ll just stop using Gmail altogether.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I Have Organized All Of My Photos Into a Single Location And Service</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/healing/i-have-organized-all-of-my-photos-into-a-single-lcoation-and-service-copy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I Have Organized All Of My Photos Into a Single Location And Service" /><published>2019-07-09T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-07-08T12:25:52-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/healing/i-have-organized-all-of-my-photos-into-a-single-lcoation-and-service%20copy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/healing/i-have-organized-all-of-my-photos-into-a-single-lcoation-and-service-copy/">&lt;p&gt;After almost four weeks worth of work I finally managed to download all of my photos from a variety of services, and backup storage designations, de-duplicated them, and uploaded all of them to a single service–iPhoto. I went through Flickr, Instagram, Facebook, Dropbox, Google, Amazon, Apple, as well as some local file stores and aggregated all of my photos into a single place. I had to do it in waves on my laptop, because I have so many photos, it all didn’t fit on my hard drive. Eventually I was able to get them all onto my local hard drive after about twenty separate de-duplication jobs. Once done, I still couldn’t get them imported into iPhotos without moving to an external drive and importing in several batches from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process really demonstrated for me how technology platforms lock us in with the volume of data we generate via their applications. The problem with my approach to managing my photos is that I have chased the free or low costing photo provider for almost 20 years, resulting in my photos being spread across numerous providers. As I wrote before, all of this just feels like an emotional trap, inviting photo service providers to get their hooks in me, and not allowing me to move on. I know it was one of the main reasons I stayed with Flickr through two acquisitions, and it was one of the major cords I cut allowing me to get a handle on my Facebook and Instagram accounts. An unorganized massive store of personal photos just opens you up to manipulation by service providers, and there is no reason we should put ourselves in these positions—contributing to the sprawl that is our digital self, while giving platforms the upper hand when it comes to locking us in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a reason Flickr, Facebook, Instagram, and Google allow us to store so many photos for free. It locks us in to using their platforms, and having their applications on our desktop, laptop, and mobile devices. Not having our photos well organized and usable (without the help of their platform) is by design. Making it so you’ll upload, and continually upload gigabytes of photo data is by design. Making it hard for you to leave is by design. Allowing my photos to become such emotional baggage, and letting them sprawl all over public and private locations across the web is just irresponsible of me. And now that I have them cleaned up I can really feel the difference. I have them all in one location. I no longer have zipped up folders of images over there, and often overlapping duplicates over there. I have them in one place where I can organize them, delete the extraneous ones, beginning the hard work of curating my collection to make more meaningful and useful in my work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually use many of my photos in my digital storytelling, so it is important to me to have them organized so that I can put them to work. I also didn’t like having so many photos with dead-end emotional attachments to them, residing in the different photo catalogs I frequented. Nothing like coming across your old photos of the ex-wife when looking for a photo to use in your morning blog post. Or coming across the angry aggressive ex-husband of your sister on a regular basis. Without any order, I was regularly wading through an emotional cesspool of information. Rendering all of my photos pretty useless. Now I can clean up, send them to the people who they will matter to, and eliminate meaningless clutter on my end, which ends us just either costing me money to store, or makes my personal life a vector for Facebook, Google, and others to just mine data from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel like a weight has been lifted. I still have a lot of house keeping to conduct on my photos, but at least they are in one place. I know that any work I do won’t have to be redone against another batch, or after I merge with some older photos from a previous service or device. I now have one place to store and organize my photos. I now have one place to browse and search for my photos when I need them. I now have a process for cleaning up, reducing unnecessary digital bits, and limiting my exposure to just a single photos service provider. I am still uploading select photos to Facebook, Instagram, and other places, but I regularly clean this up after time has passed, and I know that originals always reside in a single location. I cannot articulate what load has been lifted for me with all of this work. A load I’ve been carrying for 20 years, and I am only now coming to realize the impact this digital layer of my existence was actually having my physical self.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ki Lane</name></author><category term="Photos" /><summary type="html">After almost four weeks worth of work I finally managed to download all of my photos from a variety of services, and backup storage designations, de-duplicated them, and uploaded all of them to a single service–iPhoto. I went through Flickr, Instagram, Facebook, Dropbox, Google, Amazon, Apple, as well as some local file stores and aggregated all of my photos into a single place. I had to do it in waves on my laptop, because I have so many photos, it all didn’t fit on my hard drive. Eventually I was able to get them all onto my local hard drive after about twenty separate de-duplication jobs. Once done, I still couldn’t get them imported into iPhotos without moving to an external drive and importing in several batches from there.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Working On My Digital Self In Three Phases</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/healing/working-on-my-digital-self-in-three-phases/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Working On My Digital Self In Three Phases" /><published>2019-07-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-06-26T12:25:52-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/healing/working-on-my-digital-self-in-three-phases</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/healing/working-on-my-digital-self-in-three-phases/">&lt;p&gt;I have been working on my digital self over the last couple of years, but it is something I am formalizing and ritualizing in new ways over the last six months. I noticed that my online life was impacting me emotionally and physically, and I needed to do something about it. I cannot step away from technology, as it is how I make my living, but I can work to stabilize my relationship with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help me make more progress I am breaking my efforts into three distinct phases:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Healing&lt;/strong&gt; - Cleaning up the mess I have created.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strengthening&lt;/strong&gt; - Establishing the presence I want.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anchoring&lt;/strong&gt; - Connect myself to things in the real world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’l be investing in all three of these areas simultaneously, but early on I have a lot of healing of my digital self to do before I can move forward with some of the other phases. I also ultimately want to get where minimal amounts of healing are required, and I can focus more on strengthening and anchoring myself. It will take time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;healing&quot;&gt;Healing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have made significant headway in some of these areas at different times over the last three years. I’ve known I need to work on myself for some time now, and have invested in sporadic ways, but as I said, I’m looking to formalize my approach to pick up the pace in which I’m healing my digital presence in these areas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Browser&lt;/strong&gt; - I ditched Google, and went all Firefox – big step.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Email&lt;/strong&gt; - I am on top of my inbox. Still need to switch providers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photos&lt;/strong&gt; - I have centralized, organized, and de-duped all photos.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Social&lt;/strong&gt; - I have cleaned up my history, and minimized my engagement.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Messaging&lt;/strong&gt; - I have reduce my messaging footprint, but needs more work.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Financial&lt;/strong&gt; - Slowly cleaning up the debt, and cutting the cords.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Health&lt;/strong&gt; - Making significant progress on mental and physical health.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other&lt;/strong&gt; - I have a number of other areas and accounts to deal with.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of this area is all about cleaning up and deleting accounts to help minimize the sprawl of my digital self. I don’t need the emails, notifications, and noise from many of these accounts. The more I clean up my digital sprawl, the more I feel in control over my presence, setting the stage for a healthier version of my online self, and less to exploit by tech companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;strengthening&quot;&gt;Strengthening&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I have been cleaning up this mess for some time now, I’m able to begin investing time and energy into more strengthening aspects of getting a handle on my digital self. I’m not looking to walk away from many of the online channels I tune into, but I am looking to assert more control, and make sure they work for me, not the other way around–I am focusing on these areas currently:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Social&lt;/strong&gt; - Maintain my presence on just the social networks that matter to me.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blog&lt;/strong&gt; - Maintain all of my blogs, with a minimal flow of storytelling.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Financial&lt;/strong&gt; - Developing an awareness of, and setting the stage for more investment.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Messaging&lt;/strong&gt; - Working to be more regular about messaging with key people on important channels.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other&lt;/strong&gt; - I’m still building a list of other ways in which I can strengthen myself online.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is really the part of my online world that forces me to be more thoughtful and deliberate in how I use online tools. If i’m not actively using something, and it is not bringing me joy, I should be deleting the account and not tuning in. There is no reason I should allow for platforms to harass me into using, or guilting me that one day, some day I will use or need it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;anchoring&quot;&gt;Anchoring&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important aspect of self care for my digital self is making sure I am anchoring my existence in meaningful, tangible, real world activities that make me happy. These are the things I want to do when I reach that moment online where I’m just blindly clicking, refreshing and looking for something to fill the hole. This is when I close the laptop, put down the mobile phone, and tune into one of these areas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Books&lt;/strong&gt; - I am reading more than I ever have in my adult life.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Art&lt;/strong&gt; - I’m regularly investing in my art, helping me see things differently.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Crafts&lt;/strong&gt; - I want to begin doing mosaic tile work again, getting my hands dirty.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Activity&lt;/strong&gt; - I have been walking so much, and I want it to continue.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other&lt;/strong&gt; - I’ll focus here, but keep my eye out for other anchoring things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without these things in my life, it is much easier for the online world to begin dominating my physical world. Without something to occupy my mind offline, I’ll never turn off the web and fully occupy my mind and body. These activities anchor my digital self in ways that are critical to my health and well being on and off line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;working-on-myself&quot;&gt;Working On Myself&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this is new. However, formalizing and ritualizing it helps me regularly recognize that I need to tend to my digital self. I don’t want to get to the point where I am burnt out again. Where the online world begins affecting my physical self. Being online too much affects in negative ways, but I also can’t step away from it all together. So I have to have a strategy for coping and making sure I’m not letting another online mess accumulate, that I am strengthening all aspects of my online world, while also anchoring the digital version of myself in the real world, or I will end up letting the online world dominate who I am again–risking the chance I might lose myself all together.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ki Lane</name></author><category term="Browser" /><category term="Email" /><category term="Photos" /><category term="Social" /><category term="Messaging" /><category term="Financial" /><category term="Health" /><category term="Healing" /><category term="Strengthening" /><category term="Anchoring" /><category term="Activity" /><summary type="html">I have been working on my digital self over the last couple of years, but it is something I am formalizing and ritualizing in new ways over the last six months. I noticed that my online life was impacting me emotionally and physically, and I needed to do something about it. I cannot step away from technology, as it is how I make my living, but I can work to stabilize my relationship with it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Digital Photos Feel Like An Emotional Trap</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/healing/my-photos-feel-like-an-emotional-trap/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Digital Photos Feel Like An Emotional Trap" /><published>2019-06-26T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-06-26T12:25:52-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/healing/my-photos-feel-like-an-emotional-trap</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/healing/my-photos-feel-like-an-emotional-trap/">&lt;p&gt;Like most people, I have a lot of digital photos. I have almost two decades worth of digital photos, spanning two of my marriages, several other family member marriages, and the entire life of my kid. I store my photos across Flickr, Facebook, Google, Dropbox, and Amazon. I’ve recently downloaded them all, separate out the videos (I will deal with separately), and began the process of organizing them. It hasn’t been easy to unwind this mess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’m putting into folders, renaming, and running a deduplication on, I’m thinking about what an emotional trap digital photography is. There is no way I can ever enjoy all of these photos, and there is no real reason to keep all of them around. It almost seems like an impossible task for me to ever clean them up. It almost feels like this is this way by design. Just so that I can be sold the next solution to my emotional trap, which ultimately will just become the next layer of this mess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hoarding zipped up folders of images, and stashes of different overlapping waves of images within whatever free service I upload them, feels like something that is festering, and needs attention—-pushing me to ask some hard questions about the photo dimension of my digital self:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why do I take so many photos?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why do I neglect organizing and managing my photos?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why do I allow my photos to be spread across so many disparate online locations?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why do I allow so many emotional attachments to even exist in the first place?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why do I let bundles of unusable photos to exist in the corners?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t have good answers to a lot of this. I think it comes down to many emotional factors, most of which are commercial in origin (buying camera gadgets), while others are more on the insecure and narcissistic ends of the spectrum. Honestly looking at the shear volume of photos I took after my divorce, during the time spent with my kid-boy, was I insecure about something! A condition in which Flickr, Facebook, Instagram, Twitter, and Google sure helped exploit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t healthy. Having this many images, each with their own particular emotional attachment isn’t good for me. It has to be pruned. It has be cleaned up. It cannot be allowed to continue in the future. My image mess always makes me think of stories of old native Americans declining to have their picture take for fear of stealing their souls. Except, we do not have any respect for our digital soul, and we are perfectly happy selling it to the highest bidder, feeding our insecurities, over and over, until we are stretched out across the web, for everyone to gawk at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve cleaned up my Twitter, Facebook, and Instagram accounts significantly over the last couple of years. The recent acquisition of Flickr forced me to download my history there. Now I just need to clean out the storage units I have in Amazon, Google, and Dropbox. Once I have things de-duped, cleaned up, and organized, I will find one place to put them, so that I can use them, and then find one place to zip up and back them up in case my plan A fails on me. I will establish a strategy for being thoughtful about what photos I take, and how I clean them up and organize them in real time–helping ensure this will not happen again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel like I have a lot more processing to do around the illness that digital photos introduce into my life. It isn’t just the number of photos, it is the many places where I put them. It is the performance I do with them online each day, across many web properties—mine, and other 3rd parties. It is unacceptable that I don’t take better care of digital self, curating, cleaning, organizing and being more thoughtful about the photos I produce, keep, or let disappear. It means for a healthier, saner, happier me, but it also reduces the vector for technology companies to get their hooks in me with their FREE storage, easy sharing, and other ways in which they monetize my digital self, and extract value from my daily behavioral exhaust.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ki Lane</name></author><category term="Images" /><category term="Flickr" /><category term="Facebook" /><category term="Instagram" /><summary type="html">Like most people, I have a lot of digital photos. I have almost two decades worth of digital photos, spanning two of my marriages, several other family member marriages, and the entire life of my kid. I store my photos across Flickr, Facebook, Google, Dropbox, and Amazon. I’ve recently downloaded them all, separate out the videos (I will deal with separately), and began the process of organizing them. It hasn’t been easy to unwind this mess.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Goodbye Google Chrome</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/healing/goodbye-google-chrome/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Goodbye Google Chrome" /><published>2019-06-25T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-06-25T12:25:52-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/healing/goodbye-google-chrome</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/healing/goodbye-google-chrome/">&lt;p&gt;I recently removed Google Chrome from my laptop, iPhone, and iPad. From here forward I will rely on Firefox to be my primary browser, and Safari as a backup when required. I have used Google Chrome since it launched in 2008. The gateway drug for the browser was definitely the search engine, email, and docs, but it was also the performance, and cult-like mentality of everything that was “Google Free” at the moment. Over a decade later, I just can’t stomach being so hooked into the Google ecosystem, with their surveillance business model, forcing me to further abandon as much of their tooling as I possibly can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be a continuous battle for me to escape the Googleplex of products, but removing the browser from my reality is a major milestone. As someone who work on the Internet, my browser is the most important tool in my toolbox. I spend most of my days in the browser, searching, developing, building, publishing, and researching. It reveals a lot about me, my career, my interests, and gives Google a very big window into my existence. Establishing a relationship that requires a lot of trust, and Google just hasn’t invested in building my trust, and seems to work harder at eroding it, and focusing on profits at all cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With my move to Firefox I will be giving up some performance, extensions, and other things I’ve grown accustom to. While not perfect, Mozilla, the organization behind Firefox is more mission driven than Google is. Firefox still has my trust. Google has lost it, and I doubt they would be able to get it back, with the trajectory they are on. What put me over the edge with Google was’t about my personal privacy, it was about Google being the poster child for the surveillance economy, and actively working to normalize surveillance when it comes to dominating the technology landscape, and generating massive profits off our daily experiences. I don’t feel like I will single handedly cause Google to change, but I can opt out wherever I possibly can for my own sanity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish I could whisper in my 2008 ear regarding what was going to happen with the web over the next decade, but I can’t. However, I can work to learn from my mistakes, take control of more of my digital self, by cutting ties with Google’s web browser. I will begin addressing some of my other Google dependencies, such as search, videos, email, and the other free ways they have drilled into my life, looking for behavioral exhaust to extract from my daily experiences. This isn’t a fight over the ownership of my data, or just about my privacy, it is about saying no to surveillance capitalism wherever I can, and be accountable when it comes to my digital presence, what data I hand over to powerful technology companies, and the overall health of my digital, and physical self in the 21st century.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ki Lane</name></author><category term="Google" /><category term="Browsers" /><summary type="html">I recently removed Google Chrome from my laptop, iPhone, and iPad. From here forward I will rely on Firefox to be my primary browser, and Safari as a backup when required. I have used Google Chrome since it launched in 2008. The gateway drug for the browser was definitely the search engine, email, and docs, but it was also the performance, and cult-like mentality of everything that was “Google Free” at the moment. Over a decade later, I just can’t stomach being so hooked into the Google ecosystem, with their surveillance business model, forcing me to further abandon as much of their tooling as I possibly can.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Feeling Scattered and Stretched Thin</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/the%20beginning/feeling-scattered-and-stretched-too-thin/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Feeling Scattered and Stretched Thin" /><published>2019-06-16T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-06-24T12:25:52-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/the%20beginning/feeling-scattered-and-stretched-too-thin</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/the%20beginning/feeling-scattered-and-stretched-too-thin/">&lt;p&gt;Over the course of my life, I have had many highs and lows. Times where I feel organized and put together, with other moments where I feel scattered and stretched too thin. I’m pretty good at identifying the ups and downs of my world, but in the last decade I’ve noticed a new version of this creeping into my life. I have noticed with the increase in the number of Internet connected devices that I use, and the number of online accounts I possess, I am also experiencing a new form of being scattered and stretched too thin. Something that goes beyond just my job, career, kids, and the usual suspects that contribute to how I feel on a regular basis. In the last couple of years I’ve narrowed the causes of this feeling to be linked to my relationship with the online world–the web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anxiety, and feeling scattered is nothing new for me, but I’ve noticed that being online has taken my anxiety and my mental state to new levels. Being online has connected me to new opportunities, but it has also resulted in many competing interests on my time, energy, and focus. Beginning with my email inbox, to Facebook and Twitter, and all the apps, notifications, and other mobile, desktop, and devices. There are many ways in which platform services are getting their hooks in me, tracking my location, understanding my behavior, and targeting me. There are hundreds of different services trying to get a piece of me on any given day via my mobile phone, laptop computer, and the other devices that have infiltrated my life. All working to mine, extract, and scatter pieces of me around the web, stored on the cloud servers of hundreds of different companies around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many companies I have entered into some sort of agreement, based upon the services they offer and the terms of services they provide me as a user. I need to regularly review these arrangements, justify their utility in my life, and work to maintain these accounts and relationships. However, there are hundreds more that I am not even aware of. Companies who provide services to the companies I engage with, and in some cases, secretly buy and sell information from companies that I have done business with. My digital bits, from photos, videos, and audio to personal details about my search history, location, and other data is spread across thousands of companies, in hundreds of different geographic jurisdictions. Mostly without my knowledge, input, or awareness that pieces of me are owned, tracked, and directed by people I do not know–no wonder I feel so scattered and stretched thin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the distribution of my bits online is within my control. I can clean up, maintain, and even delete my accounts. I can ask to be removed from email and mail distribution lists. However, there is also a significant portion of this digital sprawl of my life in which I have no control over. My address, SSN, phone number and other bits are floating around amongst creditors who may or ay not have done business with me. Many technology companies are developing machine learning models by training on data that includes information about my life. Entire industries have emerged where fortunes are made by mining the digital bits of people like me–with no consideration for me as a human being, or that these bits belong to me. The current stance of entrepreneurs and investors building technology companies is that these bits are free for the taking, all you have to do is develop a platform, application or device which will mine the digital bits of users, their friends, and those who come in contact with their operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am tired of being stretched so thin. I’m getting to work on cleaning house of the accounts that are within my control. Pruning the information I share with some companies I engage with, while shutting down the accounts of others I do not use anymore, or do not agree with their data handling practices. Asking myself if I truly need this platform, application, service, and device in my life. If it does not bring me joy and value then I should not be sharing my digital bits with this entity. Limiting the sprawl of my digital self, where it is within my control. Once I’ve done more work in this area, I will begin addressing the harder question regarding how do I limit the sprawl of my digital self across companies I do not directly deal with–a situation that will be much harder to address, and will take more time and potentially policy level work to make the change I envision. Helping me protect my digital self, and minimize the abuse and exploitation of my self in an online environment, as well as limiting negative situations that can spill over into the physical world.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ki Lane</name></author><category term="Beginning" /><summary type="html">Over the course of my life, I have had many highs and lows. Times where I feel organized and put together, with other moments where I feel scattered and stretched too thin. I’m pretty good at identifying the ups and downs of my world, but in the last decade I’ve noticed a new version of this creeping into my life. I have noticed with the increase in the number of Internet connected devices that I use, and the number of online accounts I possess, I am also experiencing a new form of being scattered and stretched too thin. Something that goes beyond just my job, career, kids, and the usual suspects that contribute to how I feel on a regular basis. In the last couple of years I’ve narrowed the causes of this feeling to be linked to my relationship with the online world–the web.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hello World</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/the%20beginning/hello-world/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hello World" /><published>2019-06-15T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-06-24T12:25:52-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/the%20beginning/hello-world</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/the%20beginning/hello-world/">&lt;p&gt;Hello World is a favorite way to begin any learning experience in a computational world, so it seems like a fitting place to begin this journey. Hello World! For me, the world I am saying hello to is just a looking glass, where my physical self is saying hello my digital self, connecting the old me, with the new me. Over the last decade I have noticed an increasing level of impact on my physical well being originating from this new online, digital version of myself that has been evolving over the last 20 years–something which is occasionally defined by me, but more often that not, it is something that is being defined and directed by others. In 2019, I am finally tending to a burning need to understand this new version of my digital self that has emerged, working better define who I am, and what the impact the virtual world is actually inflicting on my physical well-being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I use the phrase “digital self”, I feel like I’m invoking yet another meaningless phrase to be wielded by the computational belief sales machine, probing for ways in which human beings can be sold, or sold to. However, I need a simple, meaningful way to articulate this version of myself I am seeing evolve amidst the growing digital wreckage that has emerged across the world wide web. With my physical self standing in front of this looking glass, saying hello world, I realized that I can’t let this phrase be hijacked of meaning like everything else around me, that I needed to wrestle this phrase back, and use it to define this aspect of my being before it was too late. I have spent forty-seven years working to understand my physical self, with almost twenty of these years spent defining my digital self, and the time has come to reconcile these two worlds, and make sure I’m taking care of myself in both worlds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After much study, consideration, and testing, I strongly believe that my digital self is an extension of my physical self. Images, video, audio, and data about me online are having an increasingly significant impact on my physical and mental well-being. My financial state of being, credit score, career opportunities, social life, and much, much more is being actively defined by my digital self, having real world impact on who I am. Many folks I’ve talked to on this subject laugh at the notion of me believing my digital self is something meaningful, and that could be directly connected to my physical being–these are often the same people who are profiting, and defining who we can become, and allowed to be in this online realm. The rest of us are left struggling to stay in control over our daily narrative, just trying to live in an increasingly chaotic and fast moving online environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m no luddite. I’ve embraced Internet technology. I still live and breathe it in my ob. However, I can come to see how this latest wave of technology is just one of many tools which allows a certain genre of individual-centric ideology and a wider capitalist belief system to surveil, define, and direct our behaviors on and offline, prescribing behavioral templates for us all to apply when defining our digital, as well as physical self. From autocomplete on our phones, to Instagram stories, and Alexa and Siri voice interfaces, we are regularly provided templates that define and shape our behaviors, reducing who we are to a series of transactions, shaping our everyday experiences so that they be defined, then sold to the highest bidder, without much consideration for who we are, or acknowledgement that we are a human being. After much contemplation, and scrutiny, I’m determined to wrestle back my digital self. What you see online about me, publicly or privately, is an extension of who I am, and has real world consequences when it comes to how I live my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that anything online about me, is me. Just as much as anything about me that I do in the physical world. Online images of me, are a piece of me. Online videos of me, are a piece of me. Audio voice recordings of me are me. Data about me, is a piece of me. These pieces of me, are not up for sale to the highest bidder. Sure there are some situations where I will consider being compensated for usage and engagement with “me” (ie. a job, consulting, etc.), however these engagements all still require my consent as well as fair compensation. Just because you gated your online world with a cleverly crafted terms of service that tricked me out of pieces of my digital self, doesn’t make it right or fair. Just because these pieces of me were created by me, and reside on your platform, doesn’t diminish the fact that they are still pieces of me, and the fact that I am a human being–despite from your view, I am just one of millions of human beings who live their digital lives on your platform each day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The digital self is a journey for me, to better define my digital existence. I’m not looking to take anti-technological stance here. I’m looking to reclaim control over my digital self. I’m looking to be the ones who controls the form in which my digital self takes, and how and where it goes. This isn’t the fun and silly early days of the Internet. This is my career, financial security, physical and mental health, and overall well-being we are talking about here. The health of my digital self directly impacts the health of my physical and mental self, as well as those around me. I’m tired of feeling scattered, stretched thin, and abused by so many online predators. I’m going to work to take control over my digital self, and live the best online life I possibly can. Please join me in my journey, and let me know how we can all work together to look after and tend to our digital self, in this new world we’ve created for ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ki Lane</name></author><category term="Beginning" /><summary type="html">Hello World is a favorite way to begin any learning experience in a computational world, so it seems like a fitting place to begin this journey. Hello World! For me, the world I am saying hello to is just a looking glass, where my physical self is saying hello my digital self, connecting the old me, with the new me. Over the last decade I have noticed an increasing level of impact on my physical well being originating from this new online, digital version of myself that has been evolving over the last 20 years–something which is occasionally defined by me, but more often that not, it is something that is being defined and directed by others. In 2019, I am finally tending to a burning need to understand this new version of my digital self that has emerged, working better define who I am, and what the impact the virtual world is actually inflicting on my physical well-being.</summary></entry></feed>